Center for Women in Government; Records ua685
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Center for Women in Government & Civil Society Records
1976-2003
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ua685
23 cubic ft.
The Center for Women in Government & Civil Society (CWGCS) was established in 1978 to elimination of sex discrimination in New York State government employment. The Center part of the Rockefeller College of Public Affairs & Policy and receives both public and private funding.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Administrative History
The Center for Women in Government & Civic Society (CWG) was established in 1978 to elimination of sex discrimination in New York State government employment. This mission is addressed through research to identify and develop methods to remove structural barriers to advancement; training of women and their organizations on leadership, management, and career planning; networking. [CWG Bylaws, 1983, p.1] The Center functioned as part of the Comparative Studies Center, subsequently the Institute for Government and Policy Studies (1981-86) of the Graduate School of Public Affairs, Rockefeller College, State University of New York at Albany. In 1987 the Center became an independent unit of the Graduate School of Public Affairs. The Center receives both public and private funding with its financial management performed by SUNYA and the Research Foundation. [CWG Bylaws, 1983, p.1]
The Center was co-founded by Nancy Perlman, who served as director until 1986, and Linda Tarr-Whelan, administrative director of the New York State Department of Labor Tarr-Whelan served as President of the Center's Board of Directors until the fall of 1979.
The CWG was initially governed by the Executive - Ad Hoc Advisory Committee whose members served on and chose the remaining members of the permanent Board of Directors. [CWG Draft Interim Bylaws, p.1] The CWG is governed by a 25 member Board of Directors made up of individuals or representatives of organizations interested and involved in the elimination of sex discrimination in the public sector. The Board meets four times annually or at the request of one-half of the Board or two-thirds of the Executive Committee. The Board is responsible for setting overall Center policy, financial planning, and staffing. The Executive Committee is comprised of the Board President, Secretary and five Board members. It too meets four times a year or at the request of one-half the Executive Committee. The Executive Committee has the power to make decisions of the Board when necessary subject to ratification by the Board. Nominations of new members to the Board of Directors are made by the Executive Committee. [CWG Bylaws, 1983] The day to day operations of the CWG are controlled by the Executive Director, formerly the Director, of the CWG.
The CWG extended its work to include programs within New York City in 1980 and offers technical assistance to groups and organizations within the state. The Center also contracts outside the State of New York to conduct studies on barriers to the advancement of women. [The Nelson A. Rockefeller College of Public Affairs and Policy Bulletin, p. 45]
Scope and Contents
The records of the Center for Women in Government include agendas and minutes, quarterly reports, publications, correspondence, memoranda, and project proposals relating to the mission of the CWG to "identify and remove the barriers to equal employment opportunities for women." These records date from 1976 just prior to the Center's establishment through 1988.
The records of the CWG are divided into five series: Board of Directors (Governance), 1977-1983; Board President Records, 1976-79; Correspondence, Dec. 1977, 1978-86; Executive Director's Subject Files, 1976-87; and Publications, 1979-88. The Board of Director series was divided into four subseries: Board Members, 1977-83; Board of Directors Meeting Reports, 1977-83; Executive Committee, 1978-81; and Board Correspondence, 1978-86. These records were created and maintained by the Administrative Office of the CWG for Center and Board operations. The Board President Records are the records retained by the CWG of the first Board President and co-founder Linda Tarr-Whelan. They contain material predating the Center's establishment. The Correspondence series contain the day files of the CWG arranged chronologically by year, month and day. These day files were kept because there are no correspondence files New Director of the Center for Women in Government for the period 1977-1986. The records of the Director were interfiled with general correspondence of the Center. The general correspondence (day files) are the primary source of administrative information for that period. The Publications series includes all publications of the CWG printed by contract and in-house.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is only partially processed and is likely disorganized. Individual items may be difficult to find.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Women; Public policy and administration; Higher education and state.; Sex discrimination; Web Archives; UAlbany Centers & Institutes; State University of New York at Albany; State University of New York at Albany. Graduate School of Public Affairs
- Board of Directors Governance File, 1977-1983; 1; 1 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  This series is unprocessed and is likely disorganized. Individual items may be difficult to find.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of records of the Board of Directors relating to the governing of the CWG and is arranged in four subseries: Board Members, Executive Committee, Board of Directors Meeting Reports, and Board Correspondence. These records were created and maintained by the Administrative Office of the CWG for Center and Board operations.
  - Board Members, 1977-1983; 1.1; 0.35 cubic ft.
    Arranged alphabetically and chronologically.
    This subseries consists primarily of letters of election and acceptance to the members of the Board of Directors of CWG. More substantive correspondence and some newsclippings on topics such as the establishment of the CWG, CWG training programs, workshops and research issues on comparable worth, career mobility and career ladders in State Government, discrimination, and Day Care Centers for State employees can be found in the following Board Member files: Karen Burnstein, Frances Berko, William McGowan, Robert E. Quinn, Delores Schmidt, Aldo Baaklini, Linda Tarr-Whelan, Pamela Tate and Anne Nelson. These files contain both correspondence to and from these Board members.
  - Executive Committee, 1978-1981; 1.2; 0.175 cubic ft.
    Semi-chronological arrangement.
    This subseries consists of correspondence, agendas, and minutes of the Executive Committee of the CWG Board of Directors. The major topics included are bylaws, nominations to the Board, funding, the CWG New York City project (1980-81), and pay equity study (1979-81), and training programs.
  - Board of Directors Meeting Reports, 1977-1983; 1.3; 0.35 cubic ft.
    Arranged chronologically
    This subseries consists of quarterly reports of the Board of Directors which include agendas and minutes, the Director's Report to the BD, and the Financial Report. Some contain bylaws, but no financial report. Minutes are those of the previous meeting. Missing are the reports for March, 1979 and September, 1983. Topics covered in these reports include comparable worth/pay equity (1979-83), career mobility (1979-83), sexual harassment (1980-83), affirmative action, office technology, race and sex discrimination, and; CWG staffing, training programs, public education/networking and fund raising. This subseries also includes Board Lists for 1980, 1981 and 1982.
  - Board Correspondence, 1978-1982; 1.4; 0.175 cubic ft.
    This subseries consists of correspondence - letters and memoranda sent to the members of the Board. Topics covered include changes in the CWG Board, BM conflicts of interest, CWG mission, nominations/elections to the Board, grants and donations, and issues such as career ladders, pay equity, rape legislation, and NYC Advisor Program. This subseries also includes the records of the Executive - Ad Hoc Advisory Committee consisting of memoranda and letters on funding and the establishment of the CWG and lists of members of the Committee and Board.
- Board President Records, 1976-1979; 2; 0.25 cubic ft.
  This series contains the retained records of the first President of the Board of Directors and co-founder of the CWG, Linda Tarr-Whelan and consists of correspondence (letters and memoranda's for 1977-6/79), agendas, proposal notes, photocopies of news clippings, Board and other reports. Topics 'included are sex discrimination in public employment, career mobility, and establishment of the CWG, affirmative action, funding and career planning. Some of the information contained in these files predate the founding of the CWG in 1978.
- Correspondence (Day Files), 1977-1986; 3; 3.5 cubic ft.
  Arranged chronologically.
  Contains 1979-83 day files preceded by general incoming and outgoing correspondence files. This series consists of the central day files of the CWG. It includes letters, form letters, memoranda, project proposals, and project updates. Topics covered in this series includes career ladders, career mobility (1979-85), sex discrimination and discrimination of the handicapped, women and minority advancement, comparable worth/pay equity 1979-86), child care, and sexual harassment (1979-83), as well as Center training programs, and funding.
- Executive Director's Subject Files, 1976-1988; 4; 1 cubic ft.
  The series includes documents relating to the creation of the center, by-laws, Board of Director notices, minutes and agendas, and the Director's report to the Board. Also included are the Executive Committee agenda minutes and notices, budgets, financial records, fellowship programs, conferences held and activity summaries. Also included are proposals for reports, studies, and programs; bibliographies, brochures from Center programs, a news release file and news articles relating to the Center.
  - Bibliographies, 1978-1987 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 1)
  - Board of Directors notices, meetings and minutes, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors minutes and reports, 1978-1985 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 3)
  - Board of Directors minutes and reports, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 4)
  - Brochures, 1977-1987 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 5)
  - Budget and Finance, 1978-1980 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 6)
  - By-Laws, 1976 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 7)
  - Career Planning handbook news coverage, 1979-1981 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 8)
  - Conferences held, 1983 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 9)
  - Director's report to the board, 1978-1982 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 10)
  - Executive Committee minutes and agenda, 1982-1985 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 11)
  - Fellowships, 1983-1987 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 12)
  - Goals and priorities, 1978-1979 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 13)
  - History, 1978; 1988 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 14)
  - Memos and notices, 1980-1984 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 15)
  - News articles, 1980-1984 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 16)
  - News releases, 1980-1981 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 17)
  - News on Women in Government, 1982-1987 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 18)
  - Program-Managerial Access Project, 1982 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 19)
  - Program-Preparing for a Change, 1985 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 20)
  - Program-Managing a Changing Workforce, 1982 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 21)
  - Program-Underdeveloped Women Working for New York State Government, 1980 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 22)
  - Proposal-Comparable Worth, 1982 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 23)
  - Proposal-Continuing Education in State Government, 1978 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 24)
  - Proposal for Establishing a New York City Program for Women in State Government, 1979 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 25)
  - Proposal-Women as Managers, 1979 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 26)
  - Proposal for Center, 1976 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 27)
  - Publication lists, 1976-1987 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 28)
  - Publications, 1979-1987 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 29)
  - Speeches/Transcripts, 1976 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 30)
  - Summary of activities, 1985 (Box 1 (4-Executive Director's Subject Files), Folder 31)
- Publications, 1979-1987; 5
  This series includes the working papers and reports published by the CWG.
  - Reports, 1978-1986; 5.1
    This series includes published and unpublished reports used in seminars and self-help programs. The reports cover such problems as discrimination, pay equity, understanding affirmative action, bridge jobs in New York State government and hiring policies in New York City.
    - The New York State Pay Equity Study: A Research Report, 1986 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 1)
    - Alternative Routes for Managerial Promotion in New York State: A Research Report, 1984 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 2)
    - Occupational Segregation and Its Impact on working Women: Report of a Conference (Sponsored by the Ford Foundation), 1982 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 3)
    - Hiring Policies in the New York City Uniformed Services, 1986 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 4)
    - The Effects of Personnel Practices on Female Employees on the NYS Unified Court System, 1986 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 5)
    - Ergonomics: The Changing Office, 1987 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 6)
    - Managerial Access Project, 1985 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 7)
    - Alternative Routes of Promotion, 1981 (Box 2 (5-Publications), Folder 1)
    - Alternative Routes for Managerial Promotion in New York State: An Analysis of Their Differential Use on the Basis of Sex and Minority Status, 1984 (Box 2 (5-Publications), Folder 2)
    - Bridge Jobs in New York State Government, 1978 (Box 2 (5-Publications), Folder 3)
    - Improving the Status of Women and Minorities, 1986 (Box 2 (5-Publications), Folder 4)
    - Office Automation; A Survey of Government Employees, 1987 (Box 2 (5-Publications), Folder 5)
    - Understanding and Utilizing Affirmative Action: A program for Managers and Supervisors, 1985 (Box 2 (5-Publications), Folder 6)
  - Working Papers, 1979-1986; 5.2
    Working papers are developed to support a specific area of concern and are then used in seminars and special forum programs by which the center can help educate women. They report on admission of women in medical school, comparable worth, pay equity and sex-segregated career ladders.
    - Sex-Segregated Career Ladders in New York State Government Employment: A structural Analysis of Inequality in Employment, 1979 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 1)
    - Summary of Working Papers #1, 1979 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 2)
    - Preliminary Memorandum on pay Equity, 1980 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 3)
    - Women, Unions and Equal Employment Opportunity, 1981 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 4)
    - The Employment Effects of Comparable Worth Policy for Women, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 5)
    - Labor Market Inequality and Equal Employment Policy for Women: Across National Comparison, 1979 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 6)
    - Statistics on Women and Minorities in Public Employment, 1983 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 7)
    - Summary of Working Papers #6, 1984 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 8)
    - Managerial Promotions in the Public Sector: The Impact of Eligibility Requirements on Women and Minorities, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 9)
    - The Admission of Women and Minorities to Medical School, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 10)
    - Hard Truths for Strategic Change; Dilemmas for Implementing Affirmative Action, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 11)
    - Testimony of the Center for Women in Government before the United States House of Representatives, 1982 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 12)
    - A Want of Harmony; Perspectives on Wage Discrimination and Comparable Worth, 1983 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 13)
    - New Directions of Equal Employment Policy; Training Women for Non-Traditional Occupations, 1984 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 14)
    - Comparable Worth and Wage Discrimination, 1984 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 15)
    - Equitable Compensation; Methodological Criteria for Comparable Worth, 1985 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 16)
    - Minorities and Pay Equity in New York State Government Employment, 1986 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 17)
  - Curricula, 1979-1987; 5.3
    Curricula are used as a teaching tool in seminars and training sessions.
    - Ergonomics; The Changing Office, 1987 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 1)
    - Next Step, 1979-1980 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 2)
    - Sexual Harassment: Preventive Intervention for New York State, 1980 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 3)
  - Guidebooks, 1980-1985; 5.4
    These guidebooks are used to help women deal with workplace problems and changes in the problem areas.
    - Preventing Sexual Harassment, 1980 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 1)
    - Sexual Harassment; Landmark Cases, 1981 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 2)
    - Managing Sexual Harassment Problems, 1981 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 3)
    - Non-Traditional Jobs for Women, 1984 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 4)
    - Women in Uniform Services, 1985 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 5)
  - Executive Development Institute, 1985; 5.5
    The Institute is held across the state to educate women in areas of concern such as comparable worth and discrimination.
    - Institute program papers, 1985 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 1)
    - Comparable Worth Project, 1985 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 2)
    - Discrimination, 1985 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 3)
    - Participants of Executive Development Institute, 1985 (Box 1 (5-Publications), Folder 4)
- Administrative Director Records, 1981-2003; 1 cubic ft.
  Biographical / Historical
  Nan Carroll served as Administrative Director for the Center for Women in Government from 1980 to 1988.
  - 35th Anniversary program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 25th Anniversary program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - May 1988 publications list, 1988 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Capital Gains game. Game created for 5th anniversary, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Improving the Status of Women and Minorities in NYC Government: Administrative Reforms and Program Developments, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Ergonomics: The Changing Office training curriculum, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Comparable Worth Study, NYS final report, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Women as Managers training curriculum for both NYS and NYC, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Executive Development Institute training curriculum, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Advanced EDI, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Next Steps training curriculum, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Women in Public Service newsletter, 1992 Fall (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Public Policy model, Undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - NYS Women's Advisors Conference, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Comparable Worth articles and notes, Undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Materials for search for replacement of executive director (Perlman), Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 10th anniversary materials, Undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - May 1988 publications list, 1988 May (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - June 1986 publications list, 1986 June (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - November 1986 publications list, 1986 November (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - February 1988 publications list, 1988 February (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - SUNY Research '84 special supplement on economic impact "Center for Women in Government: In search of employment equity", 1983 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The New York State Comparable Worth Study executive summary, Undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pay Equity bibliography, Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Black Women in America compilation under the direction of Lillie McLaughlin and based on materials developed and published by the Smithsonian Institution Traveling Exhibition Service, Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Sex-Segregated Career Ladders in New York State Government: A Structural Analysis of Inequality in Employment abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Preliminary Memorandum on Pay Equity: Achieving Equal Pay for Work of Comparable Worth abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Women, Unions and Equal Employment Opportunity abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Labor Market Inequality and Equal Employment Policy for Women abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Managerial Promotions in the Public Sector: Impact of Eligibility Requirements on Women and Minorities abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Admission of Women and Minorities to Medical School: Competition or Coalition abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Hard Truths for Strategic Change: Dilemmas for Implementing Affirmative Action abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - A Want of Harmony: Perspectives on Wage Discrimination-Working Paper 12 abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Comparable Worth: Developments in Selected States-Working Paper 14 abstract, Undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Interim Report on Alternative Routes of Promotion, 1982 October (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Summary of finding Barriers to Advancement: Promotion of Women and Minorities into Managerial Positions in New York State Government, 1981 August (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 30th Anniversary program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Women in Public Service quarterly bulletin, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Materials on 1999 Women-Led Economic Agenda meeting (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Women in Public Service quarterly bulletin, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Materials on 1998 Women and Public Policy Fellowship program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Spring and Summer 1998 In Brief (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Summer 1993 Center Update (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 10th Anniversary brochure, Undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 15th Anniversary program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - SUNY Focus on Women June 1988 newsletter, 1988 June (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Materials on Fellowship program from March 1990 reunion luncheon, 1990 March (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - News on Women in Government, 1988 Fall (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - 10th Anniversary Facts, Undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - News on Women in Government, 1990 Fall (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - 20th Anniversary program, Undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - 1998 list of former CWIG employees (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - 2003 Special edition of In Brief (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - March 3, 1998 clipping from The Altamont Enterprise on 10th anniversary, 1998 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - March 1998 UAlbany Update on 10th anniversary, 1998 March (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - 1985 Facts (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - News on Women in Government, 1984 June (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - News on Women in Government, 1984 December (Box 1, Folder 58)